Register of the Albert Glotzer papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Albert Glotzer papers
1919-1994
91006
Hoover Institution Archives
67 manuscript boxes, 6 envelopes (27.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, minutes, internal bulletins and other internal party documents, legal documents, and printed matter, relating to Leon Trotsky, the development of American Trotskyism from 1928 until the split in the Socialist Workers Party in 1940, the development of the Workers Party and its successor, the Independent Socialist League, from that time until its merger with the Socialist Party in 1958, Trotskyism abroad, the Dewey Commission hearings of 1937, legal efforts of the Independent Socialist League to secure its removal from the Attorney General's list of subversive organizations, and the political development of the Socialist Party and its successor, Social Democrats, U.S.A., after 1958.
Glotzer, Albert, 1908-1999
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1908 Born, Ivanik, Russia (now Belarus)
1913 Immigrated to United States
1923 Joined Young Workers (Communist) League and subsequently Workers (Communist) Party
1928 Expelled from Communist Party. Founding member, Communist League of America (subsequently Workers Party of the United States and then Socialist Workers Party)
1931 European trip. Stayed with Leon Trotsky in Turkey
1934 European trip as delegate to International Socialist Youth Conference. Stayed with Trotsky in France
1937 Official reporter of Dewey Commission hearings in Mexico at which Trotsky testified regarding Moscow Trial charges
1940 Founding member, Workers Party (subsequently Independent Socialist League) following split in Socialist Workers Party
1958 Joined Socialist Party (subsequently Social Democrats, U.S.A.) upon dissolution of Independent Socialist League
1989 Author, Trotsky: Memoir and Critique
1999 Died, New York City
Scope and Content of Collection
Albert Glotzer had a career as an American socialist leader that was notable both for its long duration and for the number of bases touched in the course of his evolution from communism to social democracy. It included a significant role in the beginning of American Trotskyism. By profession Glotzer was a court reporter, a skill he put to use in transcribing the proceedings of the commission chaired by John Dewey to investigate the Moscow Trial charges, which heard lengthy testimony from Leon Trotsky in hearings in Mexico City in 1937. For several years Glotzer was president of the Federation of Shorthand Reporters. In his earlier years he used the pseudonym Albert Gates in party work.
The collection is arranged in four series corresponding to four distinct phases of Glotzer's political life. The Communist Period Papers consist of his papers as a member of the Workers (Communist) Party and of its youth group, the Young Workers (Communist) League. Glotzer joined the youth league in 1923 and the adult party two years later, both at precocious ages, and became a member of the national committee of the youth league. He was expelled from both youth league and party in 1928 as a Trotskyist.
The Trotskyist Period Papers consist of Glotzer's papers as a member of the Communist League of America (1928-1934), of the Workers Party of the United States (1934-1936), of the Socialist Appeal Caucus of the Socialist Party (1936-1937), and of the Socialist Workers Party (1938-1940). These were successively the first organizational expressions in the United States of the international communist opposition movement led by Leon Trotsky. The papers document Glotzer's meetings with Trotsky in Europe and his participation in the Dewey Commission hearings, the formation of the Communist League of America, its merger with the American Workers Party to form the Workers Party of the United States, Trotskyist entry into and exit from the Socialist Party, establishment of the Socialist Workers Party, and the full-scale faction fight that rent the party when the onset of World War II acutely posed the question of Soviet defense. Glotzer was a member of the national committees of all the American Trotskyist organizations of this period.
The Shachtmanite Period Papers consist of Glotzer's papers as a member of the Workers Party (1940-1949) and of the Independent Socialist League (1949-1958). These were the successive organizations of the group led by Max Shachtman which split from the Socialist Workers Party in 1940. Their departure with a substantial proportion of the membership capped the intraparty dispute over the "Russian question" in which Trotsky defined the Stalinized Soviet Union as a "degenerated workers' state," while Shachtman maintained that it had ceased to be a workers' state of any description and eventually settled upon "bureaucratic collectivist" as a label to categorize it. The possibility of reunifying the rival parties resulting from the split remained open and a subject of discussion for several years. Instead, the Shachtmanites, as they came to be called, ultimately evolved in a social democratic direction and disbanded in 1958. Glotzer was a member of the national committees of the Shachtmanite groups as well as editor of the newspaper Labor Action and of the theoretical journal The New International.
The papers document the Workers Party's relationship with the Socialist Workers Party, its transition to Independent Socialist League, and its campaign for removal from the Attorney General's subversive organizations list.
The Social Democratic Period Papers consist of Glotzer's papers as a member of the Socialist Party (1958-1972) and of its successor, Social Democrats, U.S.A. (1972-1999). Glotzer was a member of the national committees of these organizations, in which he, along with Shachtman and other former members of their group, came to play a leading role. The papers document their activities and influence, controversies within the Socialist Party at the time of the Vietnam War and the 1972 presidential election, and the transition to Social Democrats, U.S.A., while an opposing faction led by Michael Harrington split away. The series is also pertinent to Glotzer's earlier political history. In his later years he was conscious of being one of the last surviving personal associates of Leon Trotsky and one of the last surviving veterans of the formative period of the Trotskyist movement. He sought to record and evaluate his experiences in his book Trotsky: Memoir and Critique (published in 1989), in shorter writings, and in an extensive and patient correspondence with a younger generation of historians of the American left.
Each of these series is subdivided in a similar manner, with a typical succession being: correspondence; speeches and writings by Glotzer; minutes, internal bulletins, other internal documents, and public issuances of the organizations to which he belonged during the period; contemporaneous issuances of other organizations; and miscellaneous or subject file material.
There is a fifth series of Photographs.
The Hoover Institution Archives acquired the main body of the collection from Albert Glotzer in 1991, with subsequent increments following.
Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made Against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials.; Fourth International.; Independent Socialist League.; Social Democrats, U.S.A.; Socialist Party-Social Democratic Federation; Socialist Workers Party.; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; Workers Party; Communism--United States.; Communism.; Internal security--United States.; Socialism--United States.; Subversive activities--United States.; United States--Politics and government.
- Communist Period Papers, 1919-1929
  Scope and Contents note
  Papers of Albert Glotzer as a member of the Workers (Communist) Party and of the Young Workers (Communist) League
  - Correspondence, 1927-1928
    - Abern, Martin, 1928 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Cannon, James P., 1928 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Cowl, Carl, 1928 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Dunne, Vincent R., 1928 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Shachtman, Max, 1927-1928 (Folder 1: 5)
      Includes photocopies of printed articles by Shachtman from 1924 issues of The Liberator
    - Swabeck, Arne, 1928 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Speeches and writings by Albert Glotzer, 1928
    - "Report to the NEC on the New England YWL Training School" (with Niel Kruth and H. Sidney Bloomfield), 1928 August 8 (Folder 1: 7)
      Typescript
    - "Statement" in protest of expulsions (with Arne Swabeck), 1928 November 22 (Folder 1: 8)
      Mimeograph
  - Internal documents, 1920, 1928-1929
    - 1920 (Folder 1: 9)
      "Unity Proceedings, December 16-23, 1920"
    - Undated, circa 1924 (Folder 1: 10)
      "Thesis on Labor Party Policy"
    - Undated, circa 1927 (Folder 1: 11)
      Speech by Juliet Stuart Poyntz
    - 1928 (Folder 1: 12)
      Speech by James P. Cannon; resolution and agreement re youth league; statement by James P. Cannon, Martin Abern and Max Shachtman protesting expulsion; statement by Vincent R. Dunne and others protesting expulsion; "Report on the Right Danger and Trotskyism" by Jack Stachel; "For a Bolshevik Struggle against the Right Danger and Trotskyism"
    - 1929 (Folder 1: 13)
      Statement by Fridolf Carlson and others protesting expulsion; list of expelled Trotskyists; list of expelled Lovestoneites
  - Internal instructional materials, circa 1927-1929 (Folder 1: 14)
    Workers School and Agitprop Department study guides and outlines on Marxian economics, Leninism, the American Revolution, the Philippine question, the Chinese question, the Russian opposition, and the controversy within the Communist Party of the Soviet Union
  - Public issuances
    - The Communist. Vol. 2 no. 4-6, 1920 April 25-May 22 (Folder 1: 15)
    - Liberator., 1919 January, 1924 April-July (Folder 1: 16)
  - Communist International and Communist Youth International issuances, 1926-1928 (Folder 1: 17)
    Includes International Press Correspondence, 1926 November 11; telegrams, 1927; "Resolutions on the Young Workers League of America," 1927; "Letter of the Communist Youth International to the American League," 1928; "C.I. Resolution on Negro Question in U.S.," 1928; "Questions of Organization for the Revolutionary Trade Union Movement"
  - Soviet archive photocopies, 1924-1929 (Folder 1: 18)
    (Obtained by Glotzer in 1990s)Includes Israel Amter letter to Communist International, 1924; American Commission speech by Grigorii Zinoviev, 1926; Arnold Petersen letter to Joseph Stalin, 1926; speech by Benjamin Gitlow to Soviet Communist Party, 1929; A. Lozovskii letter to American delegation, 1929
- Trotskyist Period Papers, 1928-1940
  Papers of Albert Glotzer as a member of the Communist League of America, of the Workers Party of the United States, of the Socialist Appeal Caucus of the Socialist Party, and of the Socialist Workers Party
  - Correspondence, 1928-1940
    Includes some third-party correspondence, in part photocopies from the Leon Trotsky Papers at Harvard University. Third-party letters are entered under name of writer
    - General, 1930-1940 (Folder 1: 19)
      Includes letters by Glotzer addressed to political party bodies
    - Abern, Martin, 1928-1939
      - 1928-1929 (Folder 1: 20)
      - 1930-1932 (Folder 1: 21)
      - 1933-1934 (Folder 2: 1)
      - 1935 (Folder 2: 2)
      - 1936 (Folder 2: 3)
      - 1937-1939 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Aggarwala, H. R., 1931 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Burnham, James, 1936-1939 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Cannon, James, 1928-1939
      - 1928-1929 (Folder 2: 7)
      - 1932-1940 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Carter, Joseph, 1934-1939 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Cowl, Carl, 1929 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Craine, Reva, 1934 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Curtiss, Lillian, 1939 (Folder 2: 12)
    - Dewey, John (to Max Eastman), 1933 (Folder 2: 13)
    - Draper, Hal, 1938 (Folder 2: 14)
    - Eastman, Max, 1932 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Farrell, James T., 1937-1940 (Folder 3: 1)
    - Ferry, F. X., 1938 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Field, B. J., 1934 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Frank, Pierre, 1932 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Frankel, Jan, 1932-1937 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Geltman, Emanuel, 1934-1940 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Giganti, Joseph, 1935 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Gitlow, Benjamin, 1933 (Folder 3: 8)
    - Glass, Frank, 1934-1940 (Folder 3: 9)
    - Goldberg, B. Z., 1937 (Folder 3: 10)
    - Goldman, Albert, 1936-1937 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Gould, Nathan, 1932-1938 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Groves, Reginald, 1931-1934 (Folder 3: 13)
    - Grylewicz, Anton, 1932 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Hanman, Bert L., 1935 (Folder 3: 15)
    - Hansen, Joseph, 1937-1940 (Folder 3: 16)
    - Hook, Sidney, 1934 (Folder 3: 17)
    - James, C. L. R., 1939 (Folder 3: 18)
    - Kirchhoff, Paul, 1934 (Folder 3: 19)
    - Klement, Rudolf, 1935-1938 (Folder 3: 20)
    - Kluger, Pearl, 1937 (Folder 3: 21)
    - Larkin, Sol, 1938 (Folder 3: 22)
    - Lore, Karl, 1934 (Folder 3: 23)
    - Macdonald, Dwight, 1939 (Folder 3: 24)
    - Malamuth, Charles, 1932 (Folder 3: 25)
    - Mangan, Sherry, 1939 (Folder 3: 26)
    - Martin, Jeanne, 1933 (Folder 3: 27)
    - Marx, Harpo (to Jesse "Carlo" Cohen), 1936 (Folder 3: 28)
    - Maslov, Arkadii, 1934-circa 1939 (Folder 3: 29)
    - Mencken, H. L. (to Leon Trotsky), 1931 (Folder 3: 30)
    - Miller, Bert (to Leon Trotsky), 1932 (Folder 3: 31)
    - Milton, Harry, 1937 (Folder 3: 32)
    - Molinier, Raymond, 1933 (Folder 3: 33)
    - Morrow, Felix, 1937 (Folder 3: 34)
    - Most, Melos, 1936 (Folder 3: 35)
    - Muste, A. J., 1934-1936 (Folder 3: 36)
    - Myrtos, 1931 (Folder 3: 37)
    - Naville, Pierre, 1930-1932 (Folder 3: 38)
    - Nguyen, Van Nam, 1935 (Folder 3: 39)
    - Novack, George, 1937 (Folder 3: 40)
    - O'Brien, V. T., 1939 (Folder 3: 41)
    - Oehler, Hugo, 1932-1935 (Folder 3: 42)
    - O'Flaherty, Thomas J. (to Martin Abern), 1933 (Folder 3: 43)
    - Papcun, George J., 1935 (Folder 3: 44)
    - Reese, Maria, 1934 (Folder 3: 45)
    - Robins, Harold, 1937 (Folder 3: 46)
    - Sedov, Lev, 1930-1934 (Folder 3: 47)
    - Sedov, Sergei, 1935 (Folder 3: 48)
      Photocopies of letters to his wife from Soviet prison camps; obtained by Glotzer in 1980s
    - Serge, Victor (to Max Shachtman), 1936 (Folder 3: 49)
    - Shachtman, Max, 1928-1939
      - 1928-1929 (Folder 4: 1)
      - 1930-1932 (Folder 4: 2)
      - 1933 (Folder 4: 3)
      - 1934-1939 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Skoglund, Carl, 1932 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Solow, Herbert, 1937-1940 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Souzo, 1933 (Folder 4: 7)
    - Spector, Maurice, 1932-1936 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Stamm, Tom, 1932-1935 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Stein, Morris, 1934 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Sterling, Max, 1935 (Folder 4: 11)
    - Swabeck, Arne, 1930-1937
      - 1930-1934 (Folder 4: 12)
      - 1935-1937 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Trager, Frank N., 1937 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Trotsky, Leon, 1930-1937
      - Trotsky-Glotzer correspondence, 1931-1939
        - 1931-1933 (Folder 4: 15)
        - 1934-1939 (Folder 4: 16)
      - Trotsky letters to others, 1928-1940
        - 1928-1931 (Folder 5: 1)
        - 1932 (Folder 5: 2)
        - 1933-1936 (Folder 5: 3)
        - 1937-1940 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Van Heijenoort, Jean, 1934-1937 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Weber, Jack and Sara, 1933-1939, undated (Folder 5: 6)
    - Wolf, Erwin, 1936 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Wolfe, Bernard, 1937 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Wright, John G. (to Jean Van Heijenoort), 1937 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Speeches and writings by Albert Glotzer, 1930-1940
    - Notes from Communist League of America meeting, 1930 July 16 (Folder 5: 10)
      Holograph
    - "On the Tasks of the Left Opposition in England and India: Some Critical Remarks on an Unsuccessful Thesis,", 1931 November 17 (Folder 5: 11)
    - "On the French Situation,", 1932 January (Folder 5: 12)
    - "Report on the National Tour, February 19-March 13, 1932,", 1932 April 11 (Folder 5: 13)
    - "Statement" in protest against Arne Swabeck, 1932 April 25 (Folder 5: 14)
    - "The Situation in the American Opposition: Prospect and Retrospect" (with Martin Abern and Max Shachtman), 1932 June 4 (Folder 5: 15)
    - "Some Considerations on the Results of the National Committee Plenum" (with Martin Abern and Max Shachtman), 1932 June 16 (Folder 5: 16)
    - Notes on Communist League of America meeting, 1932 June 25 (Folder 5: 17)
    - "The Results of the Plenum of the National Committee" (with Martin Abern and Max Shachtman), 1932 June 29 (Folder 5: 18)
      Typescript and holograph notes
    - Notes on Communist League of America meeting, 1932 August 30 (Folder 5: 19)
    - "What Is Happening in Cuba,", 1933 October 15 (Folder 5: 20)
      Typed speech notes
    - "Marxism as a Science,", 1933 (Folder 5: 21)
      Holograph and typed lecture notes
    - "Technocracy and Marxism,", 1933 (Folder 5: 22)
    - "Report on the International Youth Conference Held in Luxembourg [sic], February 28, 1934,", 1934 March 4 (Folder 5: 23)
    - "Whither Europe?", 1934 April 8 (Folder 5: 24)
      Speech typescript
    - Draft article on Albert Goldman proposal for entry into Socialist Party, circa 1934 September-October (Folder 5: 25)
    - "On the Question of Fusion,", 1934 November (Folder 5: 26)
      Holograph notes on Communist League of America convention
    - "An Outline History of the International Youth Movement: From Its Inception to the Organization of the Young Communist International,", 1934 December (Folder 5: 27)
      Typescript (incomplete)
    - "Draft Resolution on the International Question,", 1934 (Folder 5: 28)
    - Statement regarding vote on resolution at Workers Party of the United States National Committee plenum, 1935 March 18 (Folder 6: 1)
    - "Hitler Over Europe,", 1935 April 7 (Folder 6: 2)
    - "Statement on the Internal Situation," Workers Party of the United States National Committee plenum, 1935 June (Folder 6: 3)
    - "Report to the Chicago Membership of the Workers Party on the June Plenum of the National Committee,", 1935 July 21 (Folder 6: 4)
    - "Motions of the City Committee, Chicago, on the Decision of the Northside Branch to Hold a Membership Meeting for Oehler,", 1935 October 25 (Folder 6: 5)
    - "Abuse in Education,", 1935 (Folder 6: 6)
    - "War and Sanctions,", 1936 January 24 (Folder 6: 7)
    - "Letter to International Secretariat," International Information Bulletin (Workers Party of the United States), 1936 February 12 (Folder 6: 8)
    - "The Jewish Problem and Its Solution,", 1936 November (Folder 6: 9)
    - "S. P. Entry,", circa 1936 (Folder 6: 10)
    - "Memo on Workers' Defense League for Chicago,", 1937 March 18 (Folder 6: 11)
    - "Sino-Japanese War,", 1937 September 29 (Folder 6: 12)
    - "The La Follette Party: National Progressives of America,", 1938 May 20 (Folder 6: 13)
    - "Statement in Answer to the Charges of F. X. Ferry and the Request for Charges by the South Side Branch,", 1938 November 26 (Folder 6: 14)
    - "What Now for the Jews?", 1938 December 6 (Folder 6: 15)
    - "The World Oppression of the Jews,", 1938 (Folder 6: 16)
    - "Do Workers Pay Taxes?", circa 1930s (Folder 6: 17)
    - "Mexico,", circa 1930s (Folder 6: 18)
    - "Some Fundamental Aspects of Youth Work,", circa 1930s (Folder 6: 19)
    - Miscellaneous speech notes, reading notes, and speech announcements, circa 1930s (Folder 6: 20)
      Holograph and typescript
    - "The Dispute in Our Party on the Russian Question,", 1940 (Folder 6: 21)
      Typed speech notes for report to Socialist Workers Party Cleveland branch
  - Minutes, 1929-1940
    Includes attachments
    - 1929 May-November (Communist League of America) (Folder 6: 22)
    - 1931 January-October (Communist League of America) (Folder 6: 23)
    - 1932 January-December (Communist League of America) (Folder 6: 24)
    - 1933 January-December (Communist League of America) (Folder 6: 25)
    - 1934 January-November (Communist League of America) (Folder 6: 26)
    - 1934 December (Workers Party of the United States) (Folder 6: 27)
    - 1935 January-June (Workers Party of the United States) (Folder 6: 28)
    - 1935 July-December (Workers Party of the United States) (Folder 7: 1)
    - 1936 January-April (Workers Party of the United States) (Folder 7: 2)
    - 1937 February 20-22 (Socialist Appeal Caucus [Socialist Party]) (Folder 7: 3)
    - 1937 December 31-1938 January 3 (Socialist Workers Party founding convention) (Folder 7: 4)
    - 1938 January-December (Socialist Workers Party) (Folder 7: 5)
    - 1939 January-December (Socialist Workers Party) (Folder 7: 6)
    - 1940 January-December (Socialist Workers Party) (Folder 7: 7)
  - Internal Bulletins, 1932-1940
    - 1932. Internal Bulletin unnumbered issue, no. 1-5 (Communist League of America) (Folder 7: 8)
    - 1933. Internal Bulletin unnumbered issue, no. 6, 8-15 (Communist League of America) (Folder 8: 1)
    - 1934. Internal Bulletin unnumbered issue, no. 15 [sic], 16-17 (Communist League of America) (Folder 8: 2)
    - 1935. Internal Bulletin no. 1, International Information Bulletin no. 1-2 (all Workers Party of the United States) (Folder 8: 3)
    - 1936. Internal Bulletin no. 2-3, International Information Bulletin no. 3 (all Workers Party of the United States) (Folder 8: 4)
    - 1937. Internal Bulletin no. 1-3, 5 (Organizing Committee for the Socialist Party Convention) (Folder 8: 5)
    - 1938. Bulletin no. 6-7 (Socialist Workers Party founding convention) (Folder 8: 6)
    - 1938. Internal Bulletin no. 2-7 (Socialist Workers Party) (Folder 8: 7)
    - 1939. Internal Bulletin no. 8-10, vol. 2 no. 1-5 (Socialist Workers Party) (Folder 9: 1)
    - 1940. Internal Bulletin vol. 2 no. 6-13 (Socialist Workers Party) (Folder 9: 2)
  - Internal documents, 1930-1940, undated
    Resolutions, motions, theses, statements, position papers, memoranda, speech summaries, and circular letters. Some dates are inferred
    - 1930 (Folder 9: 3)
      Includes outline speech on Albert Weisbord by James P. Cannon
    - 1931 (Folder 9: 4)
      Includes "Some Ideas on the Positions and the Tasks of the Left Opposition" by Leon Trotsky; "Report on Activities and Expansion Program" by Arne Swabeck; notes on discussions with Leon Trotsky
    - 1932 (Folder 9: 5)
      Includes mimeographed documents of the International Left Opposition; resolution on the situation in the International Left Opposition; response by Arne Swabeck to national tour report by Glotzer; resolution on the international question by Maurice Spector
    - 1933
      - 1933 (Folder 9: 6-7)
        General. Includes "Statement on the German Defeat" by Lydia Beidel; statements, proposals and report by Martin Abern and Max Shachtman; summary of discussions with Leon Trotsky on American imperialism; "Towards a New Communist International" resolution
    - undated, circa 1930-1934 (Folder 9: 8)
      Includes "New Advances and New Tasks" by James P. Cannon; "Appeal to the Communist Workers in the Needle Trades"; statement by and resolution re B. J. Field
    - 1934 (Folder 9: 9)